the next concept we want to introduce is
that of logical equivalence between two
different
statements now the idea here is that you
could have two statements and both of
them could be really long messy compound
statements of got lots of ores and ands
and Knots and all sorts of different
inputs and it's not clear whether those
two statements are the same thing but
just presented differently or whether
they truly are different things and the
way we're going to claim that two
statements that maybe superficially do
not look to be the same are in fact
logically equivalent if you have one you
get the other we're going to say they're
logically equivalent if their truth
tables are identical which is to say
we're saying something is logically
independent or logically equivalent
rather if it's the case that for every
pairing of their inputs all true false
pairings of their PS and their Q's that
their output is going to have the exact
same truth and falseness for every
different possible input so that is our
idea is having the same truth table so
here's a simple example I want you to
look at the statement not not p and and
we know that this idea of a double
negative is that a double negative in
English sort of cancels right if I say
that I am not not hungry then that's me
saying that I'm hungry that if I put a a
double negative in you can sort of
imagine it cancel it now let's just try
to verify that that this actually makes
logical sense according to what I've
told you which is the truth tables so
first of all we're going to go in and
we're going to try to fill in What's
Happening Here for p my two different
inputs are true and false so I always do
that first I I put all of the possible
input values that I could have my truth
or falseness of that input P so then if
I look at not P which is just sort of an
intermediate step here if p is true then
not p is going to be false and if p is
false then not p is going to be true so
I was just doing that as a temporary
thing now for the third column now I'm
looking at not not P so I'm going to not
p and taking the opposite of that so if
if not p is false then then the negation
of being false is true and so I'm going
to put a true over here and likewise if
my not p is true then the negation of a
true is false so I'm going to put a
false down here and then what I've
noticed here is that these two things
are going to be the same thing that the
the truth table for p which is a true
and a false is the same thing as the
truth table for not not P again a true
or false so this recovers for us the
idea that P is the same thing as not not
p and the way that I like to write this
I have my statement P that's my my one
and I'm trying to compare it to
something else and I use if it's logical
equivalence I use an equality sign but
one that's got like three horizontal
lines to it that's what I mean for
logical equivalence that's going to be
my short hand for it this is logically
equivalent to not not
p and it's going to turn out that
there's all sorts of different logical
forms that may appear to be very
different like not not P superficially
is in a different way than P but even
though it's superficially different they
truly are the same thing and our method
is just write out the truth tables for
both of them are they the same truth
table or are they different